本节中我们要构建认证加密系统
In this segment, we're gonna construct
authenticated encryption systems. Since we
由于我们已经有了CPA安全加密，我们有安全MAC
already have CPA secured encryption, and
we have secure MACs, the natural question
自然就有问题，我们能否把两者相结合，来获得认证加密？
is whether we can combine the two somehow,
in order to get authenticated encryption.
那正是我们本节要做的。认证加密
And if, that's exactly what we're gonna do
in this segment. Authenticated encryption
于2000年被提出，在两篇独立的论文里
was introduced in the year 2000, in two
independent papers that I point to at the
本章最后我会讲到。但在这之前，许多密码学库
end of this module. But before then, many
crytpolibraries provided an API that
提供了支持CPA安全加密的API，以及MAC
separately supported CPA secure
encryption, and MAC-ing. So there was one
有个函数用来实现CPA安全加密。例如，带随机IV的CBC
function for implementing CPA secure
encryption. For example, CBC with a random
另一个函数用来实现MAC。然后每个开发者
IV. And another function for implementing
a MAC. And then every developer that
都想分别实现CPA安全的加密机制
wanted to implement encryption, had to,
himself, call separately the CPA secure
和MAC机制。特别是，每个开发者
encryption scheme and the MAC scheme. In
particular, every developer had to invent
必须自己发明组合加密和MAC的方法
his own way of combining encryption and
MAC-ing to provide some sort of
来提供某种认证加密。但由于组合加密和MAC的目的
authenticated encryption. But since the
goals of combining encryption and MAC-ing
当时理解得不好，因为认证加密还没被定义
wasn't well understood since authenticated
encryption hasn't yet been defined, it
还不清楚哪种加密与MAC的组合是正确的
wasn't really clear which combinations of
encryption and MAC-ing are correct and
哪些又不是。所以，我们刚才说的每个项目都必须
以它们自己的方式实现这个组合
which aren't. And so, every project as I
said had to invent its own combination.
事实上，没有一个组合是正确的。我可以告诉大家
And in fact, not all combinations were
correct. And I can tell you that the most
在软件项目中最常见的错误是不正确地
common mistake in software projects were
basically incorrectly combining the
组合加密和完整性机制。希望在本章结束后
encryption and integrity mechanisms. So
hopefully, by the end of this module, you
大家会知道如何正确组合它们，不会自己再犯错误
will know how to combine them correctly,
and you won't be making these mistakes
我们看一些CPA安全加密和MAC的组合
yourself. So let's look at some
combinations of CPA secure encryption and
由不同的项目提出的。这里有三个例子
MAC, that were introduced by different
projects. So here are three examples. So,
首先，在所有三个例子里，有一个单独的密钥用来加密
first of all, in all three examples,
there's a separate key for encryption, and
一个单独的密钥用来MAC。这两个密钥相互独立
a separate key for MACing. These two
keys are independent of one another, and
都是在会话建立阶段生成的。我们将在本课程稍后看到
both are generated at session setup time.
And we're gonna see how to generate these
如何生成这两个密钥。第一个例子在SSL协议里
two keys later on in the course. So the
first example is the SSL protocol. So the
SSL组合加密和MAC，希望能获得认证加密
way SSL combines encryption and MAC in the
hope of achieving authenticated encryption
组合方法如下：取明文m，然后计算明文m的MAC
is the following. Basically you take the
plain text, m, and then you compute a MAC
使用MAC密钥kI，计算明文m的标签
on the plain text, m. So you use your MAC
key, kI, to compute tag for this message
然后你可以把标签附在明文后面
m. And then you can concatenate the tag to
the message and then you encrypt the
然后加密这个明文和标签的联结，得到最终的密文
concatenation of the message and the tag
and what comes out is the actual final cipher text.
这是一号方案。第二个方案在IPsec中
So that's option number one. The
second option is what IPsec does. So
取明文，首先加密这个明文
here, you take the message. The first
thing you do is you encrypt the message.
然后计算得到的密文的标签
And then, you compute a tag on the
resulting cipher text. So you notice the
大家注意到这个标签是基于得到的密文计算的
tag itself is computed on the resulting
cipher text. A third option is what the
第三个方案是来自SSH协议的。这里，SSH取明文
SSH protocol does. So here, the SSH takes
the message, and encrypts it using a CPA
使用CPA安全的加密机制加密明文。然后，
把明文标签附在后面
secure encryption scheme. And then, to it,
it concatenates a tag of the message. The
IPsec与SSH不同之处在于，IPsec中
difference between IPsec and SSH, is that
in IPsec, the tag is computed over the
标签是根据密文计算的，
在SSH中，标签是根据明文计算的
cipher text, whereas, in SSH, the tag is
computed over the message. And so these
这就是三个完全不同的组合加密和MAC的方法
are three completely different ways of
combining encryption and MAC. And the
问题是，哪个是安全的？大家想想
question is, which one of these is secure?
So, I will let you think about this for a
然后我们继续分析
second, and then when we continue we'll do
the analysis together.
我们从SSH的方法开始。在SSH的方法中，大家注意
Okay. So let's start with the SSH method. So
in the SSH method you notice that the tag
标签是由明文计算的，然后把标签以明文的形式附在密文的后面
is computed on the message and then
concatenated in the clear to the cipher text.
这就有很大的问题，因为MAC本身不是为私密性设计的
Now this is actually quite a problem
because MACs themselves are not designed
MAC仅为完整性设计。事实上
to provide confidentiality. MACs are only
designed for integrity. And in fact, there's
仅以输出明文中的几位作为MAC的话，也没有错
nothing wrong with a MAC that as part of
the tag outputs a few bits of the plain
输出明文M中的几位，也是很好的标签
text. Outputs a few bits of the message M.
That would be a perfectly fine tag. And yet if
如果我们这样做，会完全破坏CPA安全性
we did that, that would completely break
CPA security here, because some bits of
因为明文的若干位在密文里被泄漏了。
所以对于这个SSH的方法
the message are leaked in the cipher text.
And so the SSH approach, even though the
尽管对于SSH这个协议本身来说没有问题
specifics of SSH are fine and the
protocol itself is not compromised by
也没有因为这个组合而被破解，一般来说
还是不建议使用这种方法
this specific combination, generally it's
advisable not to use this approach. Simply
因为MAC签名算法的输出会泄漏明文中的一些位
because the output of the MAC signing algorithm might leak bits of the message. So
现在我们看SSL和IPsec。事实上，IPsec的方法
now let's look at SSL and IPsec. As it
turns out, the recommended method actually
更为推荐。因为无论你使用什么CPA安全系统
is the IPsec method. Because it turns out
no matter what CPA secure system and MAC
和MAC密钥，组合总能提供认证加密
key you use the combination is always
gonna provide authenticated encryption.
让我非常简单地解释一下为什么
Now let me very, very briefly explain why.
Basically what happens is once we encrypt
一旦我们加密了明文，明文的内容就被隐藏在密文里了
the message well the message contents now
is hidden inside the cipher text and now
现在当我们计算密文的标签时，我们用这个标签
when we compute a tag of the cipher text
basically we're locking, this tag locks
给密文上了锁，确保没人可以产生一个不同的密文
the cipher text and makes sure no one can
produce a different cipher text that would
却能看起来是有效的。因此这个方法确保任何对密文的修改
look valid. And as a result this approach
ensures that any modifications to the
都会被解密者检测出来，因为MAC无法验证
cipher text will be detected by the
decrypter simply because the MAC isn't
实际上，SSL方法中，有一些病态的例子
gonna verify. As it turns out, for the SSL
approach, there actually are kind of
你把CPA安全的加密系统和一个安全的MAC组合起来
pathological examples, where you combine
CPA secure encryption system with a secure
结果却对一个选择密文攻击是脆弱的
MAC. And the result is vulnerable to a
chosen cipher text attack, so that it does
所以SSL的方法实际上不提供认证加密
not actually provide authenticated
encryption. And basically, the reason that
这个会发生的原因是，加密机制和MAC算法之间
could happen, is that there's some sort of
a bad interaction between the encryption
有一些不好的互动。事实上，会有一个选择密文攻击
scheme and the MAC algorithm. Such that,
in fact, there will be a chosen cipher
如果你设计了一个新的项目
text attack. So if you're designing a new
project the recommendation now is to
现在总是推荐先加密，然后计算MAC，因为
无论你组合了什么样的CPA安全加密和MAC算法
always use encrypt then MAC because that
is secure no matter which CPA secure
得到的组合总是安全的。现在看个术语
encryption and secure MAC algorithm you're
combining. Now, just to set the
这个SSL方法有时叫做"先MAC后加密"
terminology, the SSL method is sometimes
called MAC-then-encrypt. And the
IPsec的方法叫做"先加密后MAC"。
尽管我们不应使用SSH的方法
IPsec method is called encrypt-then-MAC.
The SSH method even though you're
但这种方法也有名字"加密且MAC"。好
我经常使用"先加密后MAC"
not supposed to use it, is called encrypt-and-MAC. Okay, so I'll often refer to
和"先MAC后加密"来区分SSL和IPsec
encrypt-then-MAC, and MAC-then-encrypt to
differentiate SSL and IPsec. Okay, so
重复一下我刚才所讲的。IPsec方法"先加密后MAC"
just to repeat what I've just said. The IPsec
method encrypt-then-MAC always
总是提供认证加密。如果你从一个CPA安全的密码和一个安全MAC出发
provides authenticated encryption. If you start
from a CPA secure cipher and a secure MAC
你总会获得认证加密的。如我所说，事实上
you will always get authenticated
encryption. As I said, MAC-then-encrypt in
"先MAC或加密"有一些病态的情况，结果对CCA攻击是脆弱的
fact, there are pathological cases where
the result is vulnerable to CCA attacks and
因此"先MAC或加密"不提供认证加密
therefore does not provide authenticated
encryption. However, the story's a little
但是，实际上比这要有趣
bit more interesting than that, in that,
it turns out, if you're actually using
如果你使用随机计数器模式或随机CBC
randomized counter mode or randomized CBC,
then it turns out, for those particular
那么对那些CPA安全的加密机制，"先MAC后加密"
CPA secure encryption schemes, MAC-then-encrypt
actually does provide authenticated
确实提供了认证加密，因此是安全的。事实上
encryption and therefore it is secure. In
fact, there's even a more interesting
更有趣的是如果你使用了随机计数器模式
twist here in that if you're using
randomized counter mode. Then, it's enough
那么你的MAC算法只要是一次性安全的就够了
that your MAC algorithm just be one time
secure. It doesn't have to be a fully
不需要是完全安全的MAC。只需要当密钥只用于
加密单个信息时是安全的即可
secure MAC. It just has to be secure when
a key is used to encrypt a single message,
我们讨论信息完整性时，看到过有一些快得多的MAC算法
okay? And when we talked about message
integrity, we saw that there are actually
它们是一次性安全的，而非完全安全的MAC
much faster MACs that are one time secure
than MACs that are fully secure. As a
因此如果你使用随机计数器模式，"先MAC后加密"
result, if you're using randomized counter
mode MAC-then-encrypt could actually
实际上可以构造一个更为有效率的加密机制
result in a more efficient encryption
mechanism. However, I'm going to repeat
但我还要重复一遍。推荐使用"先加密后MAC"
this again. The recommendation is to use
encrypt-then-MAC and we're going to see a
我们将看到许多针对未使用"先加密后MAC"的系统的攻击
number of attacks on systems that didn't
use encrypt-then-MAC. And so just to make
为了确保安全，同时不必思考太多
sure things are secure without you having
to think too hard about this. Again, I am
我推荐大家始终使用"先加密后MAC"
going to recommend that you always use
encrypt-then-MAC. Now, once the concept of
现在，一旦认证加密的观念变得更为流行
authenticated encryption became more
popular, a number of standardized
很多组合加密和MAC的标准方法便涌现出来
approaches for combining encryption and
MAC turned up. And those were even
还有些是国家标准局(NIST)的标准方法。我将讨论其中三个标准
standardized by the National Institute of
Standards. So I'm just gonna mention three
其中两个是由NIST标准化的
of these standards. Two of these were
standardized by NIST. And these are
分别叫做Galois计数器模式(GCM)和CBC计数器模式(CCM)。
我来解释一下它们的工作过程
called Galois counter mode and CBC counter
mode. And so let me explain what they do.
Galois计数器模式使用了计数器模式加密
Galois counter mode basically uses counter
mode encryption, so a randomized counter
即使用Carter-Wegman MAC的随机计数器模式，
一个非常快速的Carter-Wegman MAC
mode with a Carter-Wegman MAC, so a very
fast Carter-Wegman MAC. And the way the
GCM的Carter-Wegman MAC如下工作：
它是待求MAC的信息的一个哈希函数
Carter-Wegman MAC works in GCM is it's
basically a hash function of the message
然后用一个PRF加密哈希的结果
that's being MACed. And then the result is
encrypted using a PRF. Now this hash
现在GCM里的这个哈希函数已经很快了
function in GCM is already quite fast to
the point where the bulk of the running
GCM的运行时间受制于计数器模式
time of GCM is dominated by the counter
mode encryption and it's even made more so
为了更快，Intel引入了一个特殊指令PCLMULQDQ
in that Intel introduces a special
instruction PCLMULQDQ specifically
特别为此设计，目标是让GCM的这个哈希函数跑得尽可能的快
designed for the purpose of making the
hash function in GCM run as fast as possible.
现在CCM计数器模式是另一个NIST标准。它使用CBC MAC
Now CCM counter mode is another
NIST standard. It uses a CBC MAC and
然后用计数器模式加密。这个机制使用MAC
then counter mode encryption. So this
mechanism, you know, this uses MAC, then
然后加密，就像SSL那样。这并不是推荐的方法
encrypt, like SSL does. So this is
actually not the recommended way of doing
但因为使用的是计数器模式，这实际上
things, but because counter mode
encryption is used. This is actually a
是一个很好的加密机制。关于CCM我要指出一点
perfectly fine encryption mechanism. One
thing that I'd like to point out about
一切都是基于AES的。大家注意，它的CBC-MAC使用了AES
CCM, is that everything is based on AES.
You notice, it's using AES for the CBC
它的计数器模式也是使用的AES。因此
MAC, and it's using AES for the counter
mode encryption. And as a result, CCM can
CCM可以用相对少的代码实现，
因为需要的仅为AES引擎
be implemented with relatively little
code. Cause all you need is an AES engine
其他都不需要。因为这点，CCM被WiFi所采用
and nothing else. And because of this, CCM
actually was adopted by the Wi-Fi
事实上，你很有可能每天都在使用CCM
alliance, and in fact, you're probably
using CCM on a daily basis if you're using
如果你使用加密的WiFi 802.11i，那么
你就在使用CCM来加密
encrypted Wi-Fi 802.11i then you're
basically using CCM to encrypt traffic
你的笔记本和接入点之间的通信。
还有一个模式叫做EAX
between your laptop and the access point.
There's another mode called a EAX that
使用的计数器模式加密，然后是CMAC。
大家注意，这次是先加密后MAC
uses counter mode encryption, and then
CMAC. So, again you notice encrypt-then-MAC
这是另一个很好的模式。我们待会来对这些模式做个比较
and that's another fine mode to
use. We'll do a comparison of all these
现在我想提一下，首先
modes in just a minute. Now I wanted to
mention that first of all, all these modes are
所有的这些模式都是基于新鲜值的。换句话说
它们不使用任何随机性，但它们取新鲜值为输入
nonce-based. In other words, they don't
use any randomness but they do take as
而且每个密钥的新鲜值是唯一的，换句话说
input a nonce and the nonce has to be
unique per key. In other words, as you
大家记得，有序对(密钥，新鲜值)永远不应该重复使用
remember, the pair (key, nonce)
should never ever, ever repeat. But the
但新鲜值本身不一定是随机的，所以完全可以使用一个计数器
nonce itself need not be random, so
it's perfectly fine to use a counter, for
比如新鲜值。另一个重要的地方是
example, as a nonce. And the other
important point is that, in fact, all
事实上，所有的这些模式被称为
带相关数据的认证加密(AEAD)
these modes are what's called
authenticated encryption with associated
这是一个认证加密的扩展
data. This is an extension of
authenticated encryption, that comes
这在网络协议中经常出现。AEAD的想法是
up very often in networking protocols. So
the idea between AEAD is that, in fact,
提供给加密模式的信息不被完全加密
the message that's provided to the encryption
mode is not intended to be fully
只有部分信息是被加密的
encrypted. Only part of the message is
intended to be encrypted, but all of the
但所有信息是被认证的。这里一个好例子是网络数据包
message is intended to be authenticated. A
good example of this is a network packet.
考虑一个IP包，有报文头，然后是封装数据
Think of like a IP packet where there's a
header and then there's a payload. And
一般来说，报文头不会被加密。例如
typically the header is not gonna be
encrypted. For example, the header might
报文头可能包含数据包的目标地址，那么报文头
contain the destination of the packet, but
then the header had better not be
最好不要被加密，免得图中的路由器不知道如何路由
encrypted otherwise routers along the way
wouldn't know where to route the packet.
一般来说，报文头以明文形式发送，但当然
And so, typically the header is sent in
the clear, but the payload, of course, is
封装数据总是被加密的，不过你还是希望报文头被认证
always encrypted, but what you'd like to
do is have the header be authenticated.
不用加密，但需认证。那么这就是这些AEAD模式的工作
Not encrypted but authenticated. So this is
exactly what these AEAD modes do. They
它们会认证报文头，然后加密封装数据
will authenticate the header and then
encrypt the payload. But the header and
但在认证中，报文头和封装数据是绑定在一起的
the payload are bound together in the
authentication so they can't
这样它们不能分开。这不难做到
actually be separated. So this is not
difficult to do. What happens is in these
在这三种模式GCM，CCM和EAX中，MAC应用到整个报文数据上
three modes GCM, CCM, and EAX, basically
the MAC is applied to the entire data. But
(报文=报文头+封装数据)
不过加密只被应用到部分需要加密的数据上
the encryption is only applied to the part
of the data that needs to be encrypted.
所以我想为大家展示一个带相关数据的认证加密的API
So I wanted to show you what an API
to these authenticated encryption with
长什么样。它在OpenSSL里长这样
associated data encryption schemes look
like. So here's what it looks like in OpenSSL.
例如，这是一个GCM的API。你可以调用init函数
For example, this is, an API
for GCM. So what you do is you call the
来初始化这个加密模式，然后注意给它一个密钥
init function to initialize the encryption
mode, and you notice you give it a key and
和新鲜值。这个新鲜值也不必是随机的
the nonce. The nonce again,
doesn't have to be random, but it has to
但它必须是唯一的。初始化后，调用这个加密函数
be unique. And after initialization, you
would call this encrypt function, where
给它需要认证、但不需要加密的相关数据
you see that you give it the associated
data that's gonna be authenticated, but
然后给它需要认证和加密的数据
not encrypted. You give it the data, and
it's gonna be both authenticated and
函数就会返回整个数据加密后的密文
encrypted. And it gives you back the full
cipher text, which is an encryption of the
不过当然，不包括AEAD，因为AEAD需要以明文形式发送
data, but of course does not include the
AEAD, because the AEAD is gonna be sent in
那么现在我们理解了这个"先加密后MAC"的机制
the clear. So now that we understand
this mode of encrypt-then-MAC, we can go
我们可以回到MAC安全性的定义，我可以为大家解释
back to the definition of MAC security and
I can explain to you something that might
定义里一些看起来略难懂的地方。如果大家还记得
have been a little obscure when we looked
at that definition. So if you remember,
安全MAC的定义的要求之一是
one of the requirements that followed from
our definition of secure MACs meant that
给定信息M的信息、MAC对，攻击者不能产生
given a message-MAC pair on a message M,
the attacker cannot produce another tag on
同样的信息M的另一个标签。换句话说，
即使攻击者已经有了信息M的一个标签
the same message M. In other words, even
though the attacker already has a tag for
他也不应该能够产生同样信息M的一个新的标签
the message M, he shouldn't be able to
produce a new tag for the same message M.
还不太清楚为什么这点很要紧？谁在乎这点呢？
And it's really not clear, why does that
matter? Who cares, if the adversary already
如果攻击者已经有了信息M的一个标签，谁在乎
他是否能产生另一个标签？
has a tag on the message M, who cares if
he can produce another tag? Well, it turns
实际上如果MAC没有这一性质，换句话说
out if the MAC didn't have this property.
In other words, given a message-MAC pair
给定一对信息和MAC，你能产生同样信息的另一个MAC
you can produce another MAC on
the same message, then that MAC would
那么这个MAC就会造成一个不安全的"先加密后MAC"
的模式。如果我们想让我们的"先加密后MAC"
result in an insecure encrypt-then-MAC mode.
And so if we want our encrypt-then-MAC to
具有密文完整性，很重要的一点是，我们的MAC安全性
have cipher text integrity, it's crucial
that our MAC security would imply this strong
蕴涵着这个安全观点，当然是因为我们定义得正确
notion of security, which, of course, it
does because we defined it correctly.
那么我们看会出错的，事实上容易产生这种伪造
So let's see what would go wrong, if, in
fact, it was easy to produce this type of
我会告诉大家一种在"先加密后MAC"系统上的
forgery. So what I'll do is I'll show you
a chosen cipher text attack on the
选择密文攻击。由于这个系统有一种选择密文攻击
resulting encrypt-then-MAC system. And
since the system has a chosen cipher text
这就意味着它不提供认证加密
attack on it, it necessarily means that it
doesn't provide authenticated
我们来看看。一开始，攻击者发送两个信息
encryption. So let's see. So the
adversary's gonnna start by sending two
M0和M1。通常他会收到
messages, M0 and M1. And he's gonna
receive, as usual, the encryption of one
M0或M1的加密结果。由于我们使用"先加密后MAC"
of them, either the encryption of M0 or
the encryption of M1. And since we're
攻击者收到的密文我们记为C0
using encrypt-then-MAC, the adversary
receives the cipher text we'll call it C0
C0上有一MAC。我们说过，给定信息的MAC
and a MAC on the cipher text C0.
Well now we said that given the MAC on
攻击者可以产生同样信息的另一个MAC
a message the adversary can produce
another MAC on the same message. So what
这样他将产生信息C0的另一个MAC
he's gonna do is he's gonna produce
another MAC on the message C0. Now he has
现在他有了一个新的密文(C0,T')，是一个完全有效的密文
a new cipher text (C0,T'), which is a
perfectly valid cipher text. T' is a
T'是C0的一个有效MAC。所以，攻击者可以提交
valid MAC of C0. Therefore, the adversary
now can submit a chosen cipher text query
C'的一个选择密文的询问，这是一个有效的选择密文的询问
on C' and this is a valid chosen
cipher text query because it's different
因为它和C不同，它是一个新的密文。可怜的挑战者
from C. It's a new cipher text. The poor
challenger now is forced to decrypt this
被迫去解密这个密文C'，然后发送C'的解密
cipher text C' so he's going to send
back the decryption of C'. It's a
它是一个有效的密文，所以C'的解密是信息Mb
valid cipher text therefore the decryption
of C prime is the message Mb but now the
但现在攻击者就学得了b的值，因为他可以测试
attacker just learned the value of B
because he can test whether Mb is equal to
Mb等于M0还是M1。因此他能输出b
M0 or MB is equal to M1. As a result he
can just output B and he gets advantage
以优势1赢得这个机制。如果我们的MAC安全性
one in defeating the scheme. And so
again if our MAC security did not imply
不蕴涵着这里的性质，那么在这个"先加密后MAC"系统上
有一个选择密文攻击
this property here. Then, there would be a
chosen cipher text attack on encrypt-then-MAC.
因此，它将是不安全的。所以我们正确定义了MAC的安全性
And therefore, it would not be secure. So the
fact that we define MAC security correctly
意味着"先加密后MAC"的确提供了认证加密
means that encrypt-then-MAC really does
provide authenticated encryption. And
我们讨论过的所有MAC都满足这一很强的
throughout all the MACs that we discussed
actually do satisfy this strong notion of
不可伪造性的观点。有趣的是，故事还没有结束
unforgeability. So, interestingly, this is
not the end of the story. So, as we said
我们在引入认证加密的概念之前曾说过，
before the concept of authenticated
encryption was introduced everyone was
人们以不同的方式组合MAC和加密，以期获得认证加密
just combining MACs and encryption in
various ways in the hope of achieving
在认证加密的观点被严格地形式化后
some authenticated encryption. After
the notion of authenticated encryption
人们开始搔脑袋，说
became formalized and rigorous, people
kind of started scratching their heads and said,
等等，比起组合MAC和加密机制，也许我们可以
hey, wait a minute. Maybe we can achieve
authenticated encryption more efficiently
更加有效地获得认证加密。事实上
than by combining a MAC and an encryption
scheme. In fact, if you think about how
如果考虑MAC和加密的组合是如何工作的，
比如说组合计数器模式和CMAC
this combination of MAC and encryption
works, let's say we combine counter mode
那么对每个明文分组，首先必须使用
with CMAC, then for every block of
plaintext, you first of all have to use
你的分组密码以计数器模式，然后必须再次使用分组密码
your block cipher for counter mode, and
then you have to use to your block cipher
运行CBC-MAC。这意味着如果你把CPA安全的加密
again, for the CBC-MAC. This means that if
you're combining CPA secure encryption with a
和一个MAC组合起来，对每个明文分组，
你必须计算你的分组密码两次
MAC, for every block of plaintext, you
have to evaluate your block cipher twice,
一次计算MAC，一次计算加密机制
once for the MAC and once for the
encryption scheme. So the natural question
自然问题就来了，我们能否由一个PRP
直接构建一个认证加密机制
was, can we construct an authenticated
encryption scheme directly from a PRP,
这样一来我们可以对每个分组，只计算PRP一次
such that we would have to only evaluate
the PRP once per block? And it turns out
实际上答案是肯定的，有这个漂亮的构造叫做OCB
the answer is yes, and there's this
beautiful construction called OCB, that
它能做你想要的一切，而且比从加密和MAC分别构造的机制
pretty much does everything you want, and
is much faster than constructions that are
快很多。那么我写下了OCB的机制
separately built from an encryption and a
MAC. So I wrote down, kind of a schematic
我不想解释太多细节。我从高层次来解释一下
of OCB. I don't want to explain it in
detail. I'll just kind of explain it at a
这里有我们的输入明文，在这上面
high level. So here we have our input
plain text, here at the top. And you
大家注意，首先，OCB是可并行的，完全可并行的
notice that, first of all, OCB is
parallelizable, completely parallelizable.
所以每个分组可以被单独加密
So every block can be encrypted separately of
every other block. The other thing to
另一件事是，如我所保证的，对每个明文分组
你只需计算一次分组密码
notice is that as I promised, you only
evaluate your block cipher once per plain
然后在最后再计算一次分组密码，以构建
text block. And then you evaluate it one
more time at the end to build your
认证标签，那么除去分组密码部分，OCB的开销是最小的
authentication tag and then the overhead
of OCB beyond just a block cipher is
你只需计算一个非常简单的函数P
minimal. All you have to do is evaluate a
certain very simple function P. The
新鲜值交给了P，密钥也给了P
nonce goes into the P you notice, the
key goes into this P and then there is a
然后还有一个分组计数器交给了P。所以
你只需计算这个函数P
block counter that goes into this P. So
you just evaluate this function P, twice
每个分组算两次，然后与之前的结果异或
for every block and you XOR the result
before and after encryption using the
使用分组密码加密之后，就结束了。你获得了
block cipher and that's it. That's all you
have to do and then you get a very fast
一个快速有效的，由分组密码构建的认证加密机制
and efficient authenticated encryption
scheme built from a block cipher. So OCB
所以OCB有一个附带的很好的安全性定理
actually has a nice security theorem
associated with it and I am going to point
在本章末，我要指出一篇关于OCB的论文
to a paper on OCB when we get to end of
this module where I list some further
届时我会列出一些大家可进一步阅读的论文。
大家可能想知道
reading papers that you can take a look
at. So you might be wondering if OCB is so
如果OCB比目前看到过的其他机制都好，包括CCM, GCM
much better than everything you've seen so
far, all these three standards CCM, GCM and
以及EAX，为什么OCB没怎么被使用？为什么OCB不是标准？
EAX why isn't OCB being used or why isn't
OCB the standard? And the answer is a
这是个令人悲伤的答案。OCB没被应用的主要原因
little sad. The primary answer that
OCB is not being used is actually because
是因为各种各样的专利。我这里就不提了。
of various patents. And I'll just leave it
at that. So to conclude this section I
总结一下本节，我想给大家一些性能参数
wanted to show you some performance
numbers. So here on the right I listed
右边我列了这些大家不该用的模式的性能参数
performance numbers for modes that you
shouldn't be using. So this is for
这是随机计数器模式，这是随机CBC
randomized counter mode, and this is for
randomized CBC. And you can see also the
大家还可以看到CBC-MAC的性能和CBC加密的性能基本一样
performance of CBC MAC is basically the
same as the performance of CBC encryption.
现在这里是认证加密模式
Okay. Now here are the authenticated
encryption modes, so these are the ones
所以这些是大家应当使用的模式了，
右边的大家不要用
that you're supposed to using, these
you're not supposed to be using on their
这两个，大家永远不应该使用这两个
own, right. These two, you should never
ever use these two because they only
因为它们只提供CPA安全，它们不提供
对抗主动攻击的安全性
provide CPA security, they don't
actually provide security against active
大家只应该使用认证加密来进行加密
attacks. You're only supposed to use
authenticated encryption for encryption.
所以我列了这三个标准的性能参数
And so I listed performance numbers
for the three standards. And let me remind
让我提醒大家，GCM使用了非常快速的哈希函数。
然后它在加密中使用了计数器模式
you that GCM basically uses a very fast
hash. And then it uses counter mode for
你可以看到，计数器模式的GCM的开销
actual encryption. And you can see that
the overhead of GCM over counter mode is
相对是很小的。CCM和EAX都使用了一个
基于分组密码的加密
relatively small. CCM and EAX both use a
block cipher based encryption and a
和一个基于分组密码的MAC。因此它们的运行时间
大约是计数器模式的两倍
block cipher based MAC. And as a result
they're about twice as slow as counter
大家看到，OCB是这些当中最快的
modes. You see that OCB is actually the
fastest of these, primarily because it
主要因为它对每个明文分组只使用一次分组密码
only use the block cipher once per message
block. So based on these performance
根据这些性能参数，大家会认为GCM正是
应该一直使用的正确模式
numbers, you would think that GCM is
exactly the right mode to always use. But
但实际上，如果你在空间有限的硬件设备上，GCM并不理想
it turns out if you're on the space
constrained hardware, GCM is not ideal.
主要是因为它的实现需要比其他两个模式更多的代码
Primarily because its implementation
requires larger code than the other two
但是，如我所说，Intel特地加了指令
modes. However, as I said, Intel
specifically added instructions to speed
来加速GCM模式。因此在Intel体系结构上实现GCM
up GCM mode. And as a result, implementing
GCM on an Intel architecture takes
只需要很少的代码。但在其他硬件平台上，
比如说智能卡或其他受限的硬件环境
very little code. But on other hardware
platforms, say in smart cards or other
实现GCM的代码大小会比其他两个模式
constrained environments, the code size
for implementing GCM would be considerably
大得多。但如果代码大小不受限制的话
larger than for the other two modes. But
if code size is not a constraint then GCM
那么GCM是正确的选择。总结一下本节，我想再说一次
is the right mode to use. So to summarize
this segment I want to say it one more
当你想加密信息时，你必须使用认证加密模式
time that when you want to encrypt
messages you have to use an authenticated
推荐的方法是使用这些标准中的一个
encryption mode and the recommended way to
do it is to use one of the standards,
这三个标准中的一个，以提供认证加密
namely one of these three modes for
providing authenticated encryption.
不要自己实现加密机制。换句话说
Don't implement the encryption scheme yourself.
In other words don't implement
不要自己先加密后MAC，就使用三个标准中的一个
encrypt-then-MAC yourself. Just use one of these
three standards. Many crypto libraries
现在许多密码学库提供了这三种模式的标准API
now provide standard API's for these three
modes and these are the one's you should
你应该使用这些，而不是别的。下一节，我们要看
be using and nothing else. In the next
segment we're going to see what else can
当你试图自己实现认证加密时，还会发生什么错误
go wrong when you try to implement
authenticated encryption by yourself.